今天的《造物小百科》：
Today on How It's Made:
牙签，工业规模的木雕工艺
Toothpicks, wood carving on an industrial scale,
亚克力浴缸，从模具到喷漆的全程揭秘
acrylic bathtubs from mold to spray and beyond,
直升机，深入探访一架直升机的诞生
helicopters, a detailed look at the birth of a chopper.
还有啤酒，我们喝得够多了，来看看它是怎么做的
And beer, we drink enough of it, so here's how they make it.
但首先
But first,
有人用它们串起餐前小点
some people use them to hold together hors d'oeuvres,
也有人用它们搭建著名建筑和桥梁的模型
while others make scale models of famous buildings and bridges out of them.
还有人用它们来履行本分职责
Some even use them for their primary purpose,
清除卡在牙缝里的食物残渣
to remove food caught between their teeth.
欢迎来到生产小小牙签的工厂
Welcome to the factory that makes the humble toothpick.
制造牙签的原料很简单：
The raw materials for making toothpicks is simple:
原木，大量的原木，准确说是桦木
logs, and lots of them, birch logs to be exact.
进入剥皮机后，它们的蜕变便开始了
And so begins their transformation as they enter the debarker.
树皮虽不能用来做牙签，却也大有用处
Although the bark can't be used for the toothpicks, it does play a role.
它被卖给邻近的工厂作燃料
It's sold to a neighbouring factory where it's used as fuel.
剥皮机分两步作业
The debarker works in two steps.
两次处理后，得到完美圆柱形的木卷，更便于加工
With two passes, it produces a log roll that's perfectly cylindrical and easier to mill.
这台名副其实的"展开机"像撕卷纸一样剥离原木
The aptly named unraveling machine strips the log as if it
用12把细刃将其削成薄片
were a roll of paper, slicing it with 12 fine blades.
只有锋利如剃刀的器具才能如此轻松地分解树木
Only razor sharp implements can reduce a tree so easily.
同样的刀片稍后还会用来切割牙签
These same blades will be used later to cut toothpicks.
下一道工序中，原木很快变身成坯料
The logs are quickly transformed in the next stage of the process: the billets.
边切割边卷绕，就形成了坯料
As they're cut, they're rolled, forming the billet itself.
完成后成卷的胚料，被送往冲压机
Completed strips, each a cylinder of coiled trunk, are taken to the puncher.
在张力绷紧与滚筒引导下，扁形牙签冲压机把坯条切成大小一致的碎段
Held taut and roller guided, the flat toothpick puncher cuts the billet strips into small, equal-sized pieces.
并让它们源源不断地送出
And discharges them in a steady flow.
刀片以惊人速度每分钟落下2000次
At an intense speed, the knives come down 2,000 times per minute
短短60秒内总计切割出8000根牙签
to cut a total of 8,000 toothpicks in just 60 seconds.
切好的牙签顺着滑槽飞速送进储料槽
Cut toothpicks are spirited away by a chute that leads to a holding tank.
此时木材仍然柔软
At this stage, the wood is still soft,
所以要在巨型烘干机中120℃处理4小时使其硬化
so needs to be hardened in monster dryers for four hours at 120 degrees centigrade.
接着牙签被送往抛光机
Then the toothpicks are transferred to the polisher.
4小时里，滑石粉与摩擦共舞
For four hours, a simple dance between talcum powder and friction
打磨出光洁完美的牙签
creates a perfectly smooth toothpick.
牙签离开抛光机后经过筛分机，滤除破损的次品
They exit the polisher and pass through a sifter, which filters out broken picks.
完好的牙签继续进入鼓风机
Those in good condition continue to an air blower,
在此吹除受损的牙签
where any damaged pieces are ejected.
完美的牙签被气流吹送到传送带上
The perfect toothpicks are air blown onto a conveyor.
末端的滚筒确保按量分配
Drums at the end assure quantity distribution
随后被送往自动包装机
before they're carried towards the automatic packagers.
机器把牙签排列到位
Machines jockey the sticks into position,
再折好待装的纸盒
then fold boxes ready for filling.
包装机校准为每盒装650根牙签
The packagers are calibrated to place 650 toothpicks
每小时装出惊人的1150盒
per container and fill a staggering 1,150 boxes an hour.
总之，每小时要处理74.75万根牙签
All in all, it handles 747,500 toothpicks every hour.
另一条生产线上，牙签被单独包装
In a separate operation, toothpicks are individually wrapped for distribution
供应给餐馆和航空公司
to restaurants and airlines.
这台机器每分钟封装1200根牙签
This machine seals 1,200 toothpicks per minute,
自动完成包纸、上胶和裁切
automatically wrapping, gluing, and cutting the paper.
这家工厂每天能生产
This factory can manufacture the astronomical number
多达2021.76万根牙签
of 20,217,600 toothpicks every day.
从历史来看，人类并不算爱干净
Historically speaking, humans are not the cleanest.
每天洗澡是相对新近的习惯
Bathing daily is a relatively new phenomenon.
过去人们只在必要时才洗澡
People used to take baths only when necessary
或是生日那天，以先到者为准
or on their birthday, whichever came first.
在浴缸里消磨一个下午，是少数幸运儿的日常奢侈
Whiling away the afternoon in a tub is for the lucky few, an everyday luxury.
现代浴缸是21世纪复合材料与古老需求的结合
Modern bathtubs are a marriage between 21st century composites and age-old needs.
设计师借助设计软件探索新造型，追求极致舒适
The designer explores new shapes via design software to achieve supreme comfort.
虚拟设计完成后，就制作出实体模型
From the virtual, a model is produced.
这个按1/6比例制作的模型，材质是纸板
This one, made on 1/6 scale, is cardboard.
其他模型则是黏土或泡沫塑料制成
But other models are clay or polystyrene.
于是，制造浴缸的流程开始了
And so the process of making the bathtub begins.
亚克力板材用陶瓷发热元件加热到200℃
An acrylic sheet is heated to 200 degrees centigrade with ceramic elements.
直到它变得柔软可塑
When it becomes soft and malleable.
模具上成千上万的小孔协同工作，用真空吸住板材
In perfect harmony, thousands of tiny holes in the mould suction the sheet
塑造出完美的形状
by vacuum, creating the perfect shape.
颇有些异想天开的装置中，风机为模具降温
In Heath Robinson style, the mould is cooled as ventilators lower its
希思·罗宾逊：英式漫画式复杂装置
短短4分钟内将温度降至77℃
temperature to 77 degrees in just four minutes.
风机随后移开
The ventilators make way.
仅重16公斤，轻松即可取出
Weighing a mere 16 kilos, the mould is easily removed.
用另一块亚克力板材，另一台机器制作出同样完美的模具
With another acrylic sheet, a separate machine creates its own perfectly formed mould.
新浴缸看似结实，却承受不住水或沐浴者的重量
The new mould may look solid, but it couldn't take the weight of water or bather,
所以要用玻璃纤维加固
so it's reinforced with fiberglass.
在不断旋转中，玻璃纤维丝与树脂混合
In a never-ending twirl, the fiberglass strands are mixed with resin,
再由机械臂吹附到模具上
and then blown onto the mould by a robotic arm.
玻璃纤维与树脂发生化学反应
A chemical reaction between the fiberglass and the
形成坚固的外壳
resin produces a reinforced shell.
表面黏稠的模具被送往毛刷和滚轮工位
The viscous mould is transported to the brush and roller area
消除会削弱浴缸的气泡
where bubbles that weaken the tub are eliminated.
75分钟后，层压工艺让玻璃纤维树脂
After 75 minutes, this laminating process makes the fiberglass resin
与亚克力外壳完美贴合
adhere perfectly to the acrylic shell.
现已完全干硬的壳体被送到铣削车间
The shell now perfectly dry and hard is taken to the milling department
数控机床开始修整浴缸的边缘
where digitally controlled machines begin trimming the edges of the bathtub.
在这道工序中，机器人会开凿排水口、
During this operation, the robot will cut openings for the drains,
按摩喷头和气泡喷口、溢水孔
the whirlpool and air jets, the overflow hole,
甚至还有水下灯座
and even the underwater light sockets.
另一个车间正等待着近乎完工的浴缸
Another workshop awaits the almost completed bathtub.
安装水泵以及鼓风机的管路
A pump is installed, along with the piping for the air blower.
接着安装按摩系统的水泵
The whirlpool system then has its pump installed,
还有PVC管道，接头都已密封以防渗漏
as well as the PVC pipes, whose joints have been hermetically sealed to prevent any leaks.
最后，为确保一切运转正常
Finally, to make sure that everything is functioning well,
每只浴缸都要通过注水测试
each bathtub undergoes a water test.
历经13道工序、5个小时的打造
Through 13 steps of manufacturing and 5 hours of work
浴缸已恭候您入浴
the bathtub is ready to invite you in.
本期《造物小百科》稍后播出：直升机
Coming up on how it's made: helicopters.
深入探访一架直升机的诞生
A detailed look at the birth of a chopper
3419个零件被组装成一架传说中的飞行器
As 3,419 parts are assembled to create the fabled flying machine.
还有啤酒
And beer.
它和文明一样古老，足有6000年历史
It's been around for as long as civilization has, a good 6,000 years.
广告之后请继续收看
Join us after the break.
欢迎回到《造物小百科》
Welcome back to how it's made.
稍后我们来看啤酒
Later we look at beer.
它和文明一样古老，足有6000年历史
It's been around for as long as civilization has, a good 6,000 years.
但首先，列奥纳多·达·芬奇或许画出了最早的设计草图
But first, Leonardo da Vinci may have sketched the first ever designs.
但自此以后，这只"天空之鸟"已今非昔比
But this bird of the skies has come a long way since.
直升机在像越南战争这样的冲突中崭露头角
The helicopter came into its own during conflicts like Vietnam
丛林作战意味着没有跑道
where jungle warfare meant no runways
需要空运并补给部队
And a need to airlift and resupply troops.
那么就随我们一起，见证一架直升机的诞生
So join us as we take a look at the birth of a chopper.
直升机多才多艺，让飞行员能够
The versatility of the helicopter allows aviators to
以固定翼飞机做不到的方式飞行
fly in ways that aeroplanes cannot.
这架直升机用达索CATIA三维软件设计
This helicopter is created with a CATIA 3D program,
CATIA：达索三维设计软件
一种辅助设计的计算机软件
design-assisting computer software.
从绘图阶段到样机装配
It takes 700 hours of work between the
需要耗时700个小时
drawing stage and assembly of the pattern.
直升机由碳纤维制成
The helicopter is made of carbon fibre,
一种比钢更轻更强的复合材料
a composite material lighter and stronger than steel.
碳纤维由超声波控制的刀片裁切
The fibre is cut with a blade controlled by ultrasound.
多层纤维叠加，构成后机身
Several thicknesses of fibre are added to make the rear fuselage.
激光的绿光辅助定位各个部件
The green light of a laser helps position the parts.
接着用热风枪贴敷蜂窝网层
Then, with a heat gun, honeycomb mesh is applied,
以增强结构的坚固性
which increases the solidity of the structure.
但此时碳纤维仍然柔软
But the carbon fibre is still soft.
要使其硬化，需在此热压罐中加压烘烤10小时
To harden, it must be baked under pressure for 10 hours in this
温度177℃
autoclave oven at 177 degrees centigrade.
工件出炉，进入机加工工序
The pieces exit the oven and head for machining.
发动机舱的舱门被夹在切割夹具中手工修形
The door for the motor housing is clamped in a cutting jig and is shaped manually.
安装前，用共振锤敲击部件以检测缺陷
Before installing the part, it's struck with a resonance hammer to detect any faults.
接着，线束在装配板上铺设成型
Next, the electrical harness is mounted on a pattern board
然后装进飞机
before being installed in the aircraft.
这架直升机有超过2公里的线缆
This helicopter has over 2 kilometres of wiring.
其他机型可长达近9公里
Others can have almost nine.
线缆将连接至飞行仪表
The wiring will be connected to the flight instruments
面板，也就是直升机的大脑
panel, the brain of the helicopter.
这架飞机有9964颗铆钉，用铆钉枪紧固
This aircraft has 9,964 rivets fastened with a gun.
接下来组装直升机的后机身
The helicopter's rear fuselage is assembled next.
飞机的主体结构逐渐成形
Piece by piece, the superstructure of the aircraft takes shape.
重达120公斤的发动机即将登场
120 kilos of motor is next in line.
正在检查至关重要的旋翼桨叶的安装基座
The all-important circular plate on which the blades will be attached is checked.
安全第一
Safety is primary.
钻出螺帽孔
The screw nut holes are perforated,
以便穿入刹车钢索
allowing the insertion of the brake cable.
紧编的金属丝防止螺帽
The tightly braided metal wire prevents the nut from
因剧烈震动而松动
loosening due to strong vibrations.
四片产生升力、让直升机飞起来的旋翼桨叶
The four rotor blades, which create the lift and makes the helicopter fly,
被逐一卡入安装位
are slotted into place.
仪表板装入驾驶舱
The dashboard is installed in the cockpit,
并接通各处线缆，完成连接
and the wires are hooked up where contact is established.
机舱内部开始装修
The interior of the craft is created.
座椅、安全带、控制台、隔板
Seats, safety belts, consoles, bulkheads,
舷窗、舱门以及内饰装潢一一安装到位
windows and doors, as well as the trimmings, are installed.
直升机已近乎完工，只待喷漆
The helicopter is almost completed, and just awaits a paint job.
喷漆完成后
When done.
直升机被牵引到外部的总装机库
The helicopter is towed outside to the assembly hangar.
进行飞行测试，确保
Flight tests are performed to make sure that
机械与电气部件运转正常
mechanical and electrical components are functioning properly.
组装这架直升机，耗时110天，3419个零件，
It requires an average of 110 days to assemble the 3,419 parts of this helicopter.
这种2.8吨的飞行器最高时速可达140节，
These 2.8 ton machines are capable of reaching speeds of 140 knots,
140节≈259公里/时
最大飞行高度6096米
and flying at a maximum altitude of 6,096 meters.
啤酒的历史和文明一样悠久
Beer has been around for as long as civilisation itself.
史料记载，古人类用大麦、啤酒花、
Historical records show that ancient peoples made beer
水和酵母酿造啤酒
with barley, hops, water and yeast.
今天，我们仍在使用同样的原料
Today we still use the same ingredients,
但工艺已今非昔比
but the process has changed dramatically.
史料显示，6000年前的美索不达米亚人就开始喝啤酒
Records show that beer was drunk 6,000 years ago in Mesopotamia.
苏美尔人用它作神圣的饮品，原料是谷物，但不用啤酒花
The Sumerians made it as a sacred beverage from grains, but without hops.
高卢人和凯尔特人喝的是大麦、小麦和米酿造的饮品
The Gauls and the Celts drank a beverage made with barley, wheat and rice.
十字军东征期间，欧洲人发现了香料，用
During the Crusades, Europeans discovered spices and flavoured the
肉桂和月桂叶给饮品调味
beverage with cinnamon and laurel.
15世纪，啤酒花作为一种香料被引入
In the 15th century, hops were introduced as a spice,
这才诞生了我们今天所熟知的啤酒
giving rise to the beer we know today.
欢迎来到许多人的梦想之地——啤酒厂
Welcome to the fantasy of many, a brewery, a beer factory.
简单说，啤酒是一种发酵饮品
Put simply, beer is a fermented beverage.
由谷物和水酿制而成
Made with cereals and water.
首先到场的是麦芽大麦
First to arrive is the malted barley.
这家工厂拥有自己的水过滤系统
This facility has its own water filtration plant.
使用前会再次过滤，去除氯
It will be refiltered before being used to eliminate chlorine.
这个储罐可容纳8万升水
This tank can hold 80,000 litres of water.
加入10至15吨麦芽和谷物
Between 10 to 15 tons of malt and grain are added.
这款啤酒偏爱经过热处理的深色麦芽
In this beer, dark malt, which has been heat treated, is the preferred variety.
搅拌器防止麦壳沉到罐底
Agitators prevent malt husks from settling at the bottom of the tank.
原料在罐中浸泡2小时，变成一种叫"麦芽汁"的甜味液体
The preparation spends 2 hours in the tank, where it becomes a sweet-tasting liquid called wort.
麦芽汁将被提取出来，然后煮沸
The wort will be extracted and then boiled.
抽取样本进行检测
A sample is drawn off for testing.
这是酿酒各阶段众多受控检测中的第一项
This is the first of many controlled tests carried out at various stages of brewing.
这就是酒糟，从麦芽汁中滤出的固体残渣
This is the draff, a solid residue extracted from the wort.
它将被用作牲畜饲料
It will be used as cattle feed.
接着过滤液体，将麦芽汁与麦壳分离
The liquid is then filtered, where the wort is separated from the malt husks.
从麦芽汁加热器中取样，以检验
A sample is taken from the wort heater to verify the
糖的密度和麦芽汁的品质
density of sugars and the quality of the wort.
现在，向麦芽汁加热器中加入啤酒花
Now the hops are added into the wort heater.
啤酒花赋予啤酒苦味与香气
The hops impart the bitterness and aroma of the beer.
啤酒花以颗粒形态加入
The hops come in pellet form.
在控制室里，操作员掌控着酿造流程
In the control room, an operator handles the brewing process.
加入启动发酵的酵母
The yeast, which starts off the fermentation, is added.
这一过程持续7至10天
A process that lasts between 7 and 10 days.
泡沫的出现表明发酵已经开始
The presence of foam indicates that fermentation has begun.
每个发酵罐都由电脑控制
Each fermentation tank is computer controlled to
以维持特定温度
maintain a specific temperature.
化学反应产生漂浮的浮沫
Chemical reactions create the floating scum.
陈酿三周后，啤酒已接近成品
Now aged for 3 weeks, the beer is almost finished.
这些巨大的容器是灌装罐
These huge containers are the bottling tanks.
啤酒还需再过滤一次
The beer has to be filtered once more.
啤酒被澄清，去除导致啤酒浑浊的成分
The water is clarified, then rid of the components responsible for the cloudiness of the beer.
这是经过第二次过滤的啤酒
Here's the beer filtered a second time,
最终成为清亮透明的成品
and finally finished as a clear product.
回收的瓶子被清洗并消毒
Used bottles are washed, where they become sterilized.
移动平台将空瓶送到灌装位
A moving plate transports the empty bottles into place.
灌装机一边移动，一边每分钟灌装约1000瓶
About a thousand bottles a minute are filled while on the move.
随后进入封盖机，再送往巴氏杀菌单元
Then onto the capper before being sent to the pasteurization unit.
最后两步是贴标和包装
The final two steps are labelling and packaging.
由水和谷物酿成
Made from water and cereal grains,
啤酒现在可以开怀畅饮了
the beer is now ready to be consumed and enjoyed.
整个酿造过程约需4周，而喝掉它只需30秒
The whole process lasts around 4 weeks and takes about 30 seconds to drink.
干杯
Cheers.